Good.
Are you.
Jay, you may have pointed this out, but there's no roll call on here, don't believe. I did see that. So I think you mentioned it to me, yeah. So we'll just I
think you just rolled it into the call to order, I think.
>> I will. Okay.
Leanne,
are you there?
Yes. Okay, very good. And so it is 701.
I'll call the meeting to order.
And with that, we'll do
a roll call. I see
Vice Chairman
Kerme on the line with us, Commissioner Persson,
Commissioner England.
We've got Commissioner
SmithHustansson
and myself.
So we have
a full commission
here this evening. We've also got alternate
Blanchard
absent
is
Kevin.
So there will be no alternates tonight being seated.
The
next item on the agenda is public participation.
Judy said she was joining us. She's going to be a newcomer to town.
I think the other members of the public here tonight are
associated with the application we've got coming up, so we'll talk about that there.
But does anybody
of the public
want to say anything
at this point?
>> This is Judy Conley. Thanks for letting me join. I'm very excited to learn more about how
things work and getting to
know the community.
>> Well again, thanks for joining. I hope we do you proud by showing up tonight and
make it worth your while.
I'm going to move on to
additions and changes to the agenda.
Does anybody have any additions they would like to make at this point?
And I would like to make one change and just
to best use our time and make sure we cover the most important things first.
I'd like to move the new business up before the old business because
that application
is the most important thing on our agenda tonight and I want to make sure we don't
shortchange
any of the time
that we need to spend on that.
I looked, I think somebody could get by.
Who
has the music playing?
>> Leanne, if you can mute yourself via your phone
or just be mindful of your background noise,
please.
>> Oh sorry about that it's
how do I do that?
Are you on a landline?
No I'm on a cell phone.
>> If you're on like an iPhone there's a mute button.
>> I'm trying to move away from it while we do this.
>> Well, have succeeded, Leanne, and
we don't hear anything else now. So you either muted it or you got far enough away that it
doesn't bother us. Okay, sorry about that. Yeah, and Mindy,
our roll call records, I see
Kevin
Harnessen
has joined us now. And Kevin, we did not seat any alders tonight.
But
I would like to have a motion to move the new business before the old business so we can make the change to the agenda
official.
So moved.
Okay. I didn't see who said that. Leanne.
Leanne, thank you, Leanne. Why I didn't see you say it.
You seconded. Thank you.
And all in favor,
aye.
Aye.
Any opposed?
Okay,
so
with that
motion passed five-zero-zero.
And
the next thing on the agenda then would be
the new business
to receive the application and set public hearing for
application
20 one-one
for fifty seven Hendy Road.
Agent Halsey, can you give us a run through on the application for
that and
what the status of the application is with respect to being
complete or not?
>> Sure.
The application is for a special permit
to allow for deposition to fill and construction of single family
residence
in a flood zone.
It also involves
reconfiguration of
the lot lines. We're starting with two lots, they're ending with two lots.
More on that when the site plan
is reviewed.
Just for the record, the applicant
went to ZBA
for variance
so as
to allow
this use
under a special permit. It was listed as a prohibited use under, I believe it's 10.4, and unless it's section 10.
So here we are. I'm going go through the checklist one by one.
Be happy to answer any questions at any point along the way.
>> By doing that, Mindy or Jim, can you put the checklist up on the screen so we can look at it as you're going through it? Yeah,
I can't. I'm using my
iPad.
>> It on the website? It is. It's under pending applications
and it's either the first or the second
item under the 57 Hendy Road.
Can you guys do that?
>> Yep, that's great, Mindy. Thank you.
Okay, go ahead, Jim. Okay.
>> I'm gonna start.
Number one, completed signed application by applicant owner, yes.
Payment of required application fees, yes. Check-in hand. Three, evidence of approval by Eastern Highlands Health District. I'm gonna defer to the applicant on this towards the end of the,
as I finish up.
Four, evidence of approval of application in the Wetlands Commission for approval by wetlands agent.
This did receive wetlands approval some time ago.
I will make sure that the
ruling
is on the website if it isn't already.
Fire marshal review, I said was not required.
Length of the driveway did not kick in for a marshal review.
Copy of required application to other federal or state regulatory approvals, not applicable.
All draft deeds for any roads, road widening, easements, drainage,
not applicable, or municipal improvements.
Existing and proposed covenants or restrictions, not applicable.
Okay. Nine is for text amendment,
not applicable.
10, hazardous materials, none, not applicable. 11, copies of all reports
including hydrology, hydraulic and drainage, not applicable.
12, architectural elevation drawings of closed buildings
should be on the website.
Pretty detailed
plan.
Number 13, landscaping plan.
Really very little landscape involved. I mean, it's a
single family residence.
I do see a check mark. I have not gone back to review the plan
to see what what that might include.
Perhaps I will I will go defer to the
the applicant on that. Architectural floor plans, again, it seems to be a redundant listing.
Existing trees, 10 inch in diameter. I I said not applicable.
We I will verify that there are limit limitations of or the limits of of
clearing on the plan. I don't know for a fact that's that's there. I will we'll make sure that that is number
16,
lighting plan.
I believe there's a note. I to I went through this with the applicant and
asked
there be a note on the plan
just
indicating that that lighting would would comply with the town zoning regs.
E and S plan is on the is on our plan.
Stormwater management plan, not applicable.
Sanitary waste disposal plan,
it's
plan is we have.
And again, I'm gonna follow-up.
I'll have the, you have to follow-up with the status of the Eastern Highland Highlands. Number 20,
cost estimate for installation of E and S.
I believe I
have that.
Traffic impact, not applicable.
Number 22,
site plans. Okay, we do have it. Again, A2 boundary survey, again, it's a site plan location map that was added as an extra.
It was provided, it is on the website.
Title block is on
the plan.
Number 26,
if applicable.
27 is covered.
28 is covered.
29 scale is there. Overall site plan.
If it doesn't fit on one sheet, not applicable.
MAP is one one inch equal 500 scale.
There's a check mark there.
That's just for location purposes. We we have that.
So original and revision plan dates, revision explanations.
Again, those are on on the the plan that are are on the website.
Existing
and proposed grading, we have.
Structures and features existing.
Okay. That's just NA because there
are none. There are no existing. Okay, exterior HVAC equipment, not applicable.
Exterior existing
and proposed driveway entrances shown
on the plan.
Site distances, I believe that's shown on the plan. Soil test locations,
again, have that on the plan.
Existing proposed sewage disposal
on the plan outside storage areas.
There's a checkbook there. Don't believe there were any, but I can have the, I'll defer to the applicant if that had, if I'm mistaken on that.
Underground overhead utilities shown on plan.
Water supply shown on plan.
System wells and disposal systems on other properties
determined that was not applicable. There's nothing in in the immediate area.
Existing of proposed footing drains curtain drains if you remember
because of the nature of this project,
the proposed project being in floodplain.
The the house that is proposed is is raised ranch with not entail footing drains.
Hence, that's not applicable.
Existing and proposed drainage systems, any affected floodway or floodplains.
Not applicable.
Although we do have the base flood elevation. Jim, excuse
>> me for a second. Are we gonna be able go over these things
other than what you came up with?
>> Well, I would like to perhaps
answer any questions, but I mean, there's the public hearing, know, should
the application be accepted,
then the information would be gone over in further detail at the public hearing.
Okay.
Which would be the norm. Mean that is up to the chair.
>> My
intention
on going through the checklist was just if
the agent made
a block NA
that any of the Commission members feel should not be NA,
now
is the time to speak up. So we are going to try to center up on what are the expectations
that we expect from the applicant.
And then we can all go off and
study the drawing before the public hearing and make sure
the next thing we're going to do is I'm going to ask the applicant
to present his application with the site plan to us.
But we're just looking at
I've asked Jim to go through the checklist,
give us his cut, and if we don't agree with it, now is a good time
to ask questions about that as we're going through it.
>> Item 46 would be not applicable, bridges and culverts.
47 is proposed signage,
applicable. 48,
fences and walls with dimensions and construction details,
not applicable. Zoning district boundaries
should be shown
on the plan.
Number 50,
table shown on plan.
Check mark here. Have not reviewed that as yet.
I'll have to check on that.
Table of plan of parking.
This is not applicable here.
Yeah. That's clearly the that's not applicable. Mean, clearly parking is shown on the plan nonetheless. Bicycle storage areas, bicycle storage areas, not applicable. Sidewalks and pedestrian ways. NA,
fire lanes, applicable,
off-site traffic improvements,
not applicable, limits of wetlands
are on the plan,
one hundred year flood
is on the plan.
We
have a number of plans.
I understand that they're
difficult to read at the scale and they don't always expand well. So one of them is color coded.
Think the chair is going to speak to that
as well.
With that,
I'd like to defer to the
applicant really for the, or through the chair and update
on this the septic system and the Eastern Highlands review.
Okay.
Thank you.
>> Bill, were you going to speak for
the applicant
on that
as the applicant, I guess?
>> He's still having some technical difficulties.
So he wants
to talk, but is coming through a little garbled, I think.
>> Yeah, we can hear you. It's a little rough, but I think we can get you.
Okay.
>> Okay, I've had a little trouble hearing what you said.
But something about presenting the application.
>> Yeah, the question
was on the
sanitary and approval of the septic plan.
Yes.
>> I just heard, I can actually speak to that. I just heard back from them today.
Andrew told us there was an original septic plan that was approved earlier.
The septic hasn't changed. That's back when the previous owner owned the property,
but he thought we should apply for a renewed
one. The septic hasn't changed though. So they asked just a couple more questions that they wanted us to answer them on. So that's already been filed with Eastern Highlands, but it will be
hopefully approved very shortly.
It's not any different than what they approved before.
>> So there should be no problem getting that documentation
before the next meeting?
Nope. Okay, very good. Yep.
Megan, I hear you loud and clear.
I don't know if you'd be able to go through
the,
I see online there was a site plan
for I think it was called the special hearing or something that you'd written
up. Would you like to
talk through that?
>> I can share my
screen too if you guys would like to or I don't know if it's easier for
someone else to pull it up.
>> No, if you want to do that Mindy, if you can allow her to
share her screen with us that would be great.
>> And I will say my dad is the technical one on the plan so I can try to make it through.
Right you should be able to now.
Let's see.
Can everybody see that?
Yep. Yes.
Yep. Perfect.
>> So as we're looking to the screen to the
left hand side is where the existing
Hendy Road house is. And it's the U shaped
parcel
that goes around it is Parcel 2.
It's kind of cut off on the screen a little bit. But the lot line revision, we're looking to go up about
on this line here.
It meets all the requirements that you guys were looking for as far as setback square feet.
The septic is over here, which is where it had been proposed originally to Eastern Highlands.
Your well over here, the house, the driveway is proposed
pretty much exactly where there's already a cut through in the stonewall there now.
And so as Jim mentioned, it's a four bedroom house, slab on grade. So it would be a raised ranch built up above base flood elevation.
So the intention is to exceed all FEMA and local regulations.
And the construction of that, and you guys do have a section, I think it's 10 maybe seven,
that has your own regulations too, which are very similar to FEMA's. So we'd be exceeding all of those.
As well, Andrew mentioned
about the septic tank being pinned down, those kinds of things that you would need to be working in a floodplain.
I don't know if we can hear you, dad, if you have any more
to add to that
with the plan or if you guys have questions on it from what you see.
>> I did have a question on the
repositioning of the lot line up at the top near the river on this.
Know agent Hallisey said when we were talking we were going to end up with
two lots. The way you've got
that extra
line moved over there, it
looks to me like we would have three lots. The lot where you want to build the new house,
the lot with the existing house, and then you've got this other lot
off to the left there.
>> It would only be two lots. The line is going straight back from the street
to the river. I'm wondering if that looks like a degree line that's on there.
These are not my forte of reading these plans, but it's definitely one straight line or one line coming back from the street to the river to make it'll keep it two parcels.
>> I think the plan will have to be we will have to be noted on the plan that that line
is limited essentially that lot line.
There will no longer be a lot line.
Where presently exists on the back of the house lot. Yeah, I was not being I mean that'll have to be identified on the plan. That's all.
And it's not it's not except.
>> Okay, so just taking out that rear lot line on the plan, but that definitely is going away.
Oh, so
>> Jim, can you address what Jed just spoke about?
Sure.
I mean,
we're starting out with
two lots,
the existing house lot and a U shaped lot. Yeah, the lot line that you see directly behind. Okay, you got two so far.
I'm sorry. You have two so far. Okay, so the lot line that you see sort of to the right hand corner of the existing house lot
leading from the house lot to the river. Yeah. Is is the side yard
for the proposed lot.
The lot the line that you see behind existing house
will be deleted.
I mean, will will no longer exist.
You know, a deed will be a deed will be drawn up for each of these two lots.
You know, going from the river down,
you know, the house lot would go basically from the skunk, you know, follow the skunk down to the hop,
down to Hendy Road, back up to the point.
So this is
>> a lot that the house is being built on, Jim,
Is it gonna extend all the way West
to the Hop River? No,
>> it's gonna extend back to the scope
and
the lot line.
The side yard will be immediately behind the house almost.
It's the line that you see.
Just off.
If you follow
the side yard of the house, of the proposed house from Hendy Road back
to the corner to
a corner, which is the outside corner of the existing house. And
you head
back now towards
the Hop River
And then follow that lot line, you know, 90
degrees towards.
The skunk so within that is approximately
it has to be 60,000 square feet, so that'll be something
Well, so there's three lots there.
>> No.
Apparently I'm not being clear enough here.
That once that
okay.
When that lot line is drawn, the one behind
the existing house.
Lot line
everything towards the river becomes part of the house lot.
>> I'm
going to share this plan Jim because it shows it a little clearer. It's not it's zoomed out so you can see kind of the square.
>> But so the.
And I understand the confusion because it
or at least I don't. I haven't seen where these lot lines are erased where they should be.
Chad, do you understand what they're saying?
>> I do. And
it's certainly not an issue that we have gone through before,
but I can't find where
there's anything that prohibits
doing
what they're asking to do. So
if you look at
the north
and the west boundary
on the existing house
lot that they're now,
I think they're discussing
the proposed
final would have those lot lines removed. So the existing house
would go all the way west
to the Hop River lot.
So it's actually
about seven acres there
and then
a small
60,000 square foot lot
to the east, which is where they're going to build the new house.
So we're two lots now, we're going to end up with two lots
and
the reason this
is important, if it was three lots it would be a subdivision.
With two lots
you know.
>> So the line on the existing house is going to be moved to the west all the way to the upper room?
>> Either you can say it's either moved or it's eliminated you know it's the same thing.
The house lot's going to go all the way west of the Hop River. The existing house is going to take all the frontage
on the road.
Yep. With
the exception of that 40 feet.
So,
makes sense.
They going to redo this print?
>> Well, and so that was
going to be my first suggestion here. It would be helpful to us to have something that showed
the existing lot lines today
in the proposed
lot lines for the final product. So it's clear
that
with the expansion of the existing house lot looks like
in,
I don't know how you show an erased line, but I guess you can hatch through it and show that it's going to be eliminated. But the drawing ought to be clear on what the
property is going to look like in its current state and its final state so we
don't have any confusion on what we're actually doing.
>> Yeah, so the proposed lot line should be clearly
labeled and the elimination, the
two lot lines
that are eliminated
should be clearly noted as well.
And that should clear up the confusion,
I believe.
So was this on the checklist?
>> What do you mean? I'm sorry. A complete
print.
Yes.
>> And now we're going through to
see what we need
to add or modify
so that Yeah,
>> I mean,
go through the checklist and see if it's there. I have not yet reviewed the plan in its entirety to determine if we
have everything,
if it's accurate,
if it's in compliance.
Keith does
>> have two here. It's just zoomed out a little bit, but it does show
noted proposed property line here on this one. Okay. Yeah. That zoomed in. Yeah. Yeah. And like you said, these would be taken out, obviously, which it says in the application
that this all to the left would be attached to the house. But we can show those
crossed out,
you know, what it would look like.
>> Any other questions on what we're trying to do with moving the lot lines?
Because that was one of the tricky issues with respect to this application.
Okay, Megan or Bill, if you want to
continue on.
>> Sure.
So
we've written a memorandum at the time that we went through
CBA that was just explaining
as well that
Don and Bill own the house. They've owned it for a couple of years at 57 Hendy and
how
Donna was attracted to the property's unique natural beauty and
the house was dilapidated
in need of significant
repairs. And now it's been fixed up. It's no longer a blight on the town.
And since it's been refurbished, I've been living in the house, renting it from my aunt in hopes of being able to build next door.
And then Donna's intention is to move back to this house and have it be sort of a family kind of compound.
So that's been
important to us and
constructing the single family raised ranch home.
We showed the color coded map that we had
that kind of shows a little bit clearer. It's more zoomed in than this one.
The intention of what we're doing. Back to
that map, Megan? Sure.
>> And the proposed house lot will be approximately 1.3
acres.
I think it was about 66,000
square feet. I do remember Andrew saying that he added a little bit more to it because he wasn't sure how
much into the river
counts as part of the property. So, he added some to it to be sure that we were above 60,000 square feet. So I think we were about 66,000.
The remaining 7.1
acres
would be attached to the existing 57 Hendy Road
when the lot line modification is complete.
>> Okay, if I could just wait for just a minute there,
Megan.
On the application,
it says the size of the subject parcel is 1.3
acres.
Yep. And when I ran through my little calculator here, that comes out to 56,628
square feet, which is below the minimum
allowed.
And I know on you
just mentioned
66,000
as opposed to 56,000.
>> I'm thinking our engineer did his calculations wrong then when he put it to acres because I had heard 1.4
something originally from Andrew. 1.4
would be great. 1.3 doesn't quite cut it.
Yeah,
>> I think he did his calculations wrong because I do remember 66,000
square feet and like we said, making sure he went over because he wasn't entirely sure
what counts as part of the land that's in the river. Yep, and our regulations
>> have the requirement in square feet vice
acres and the minimum
allowable is 60,000.
So we got to be
clearly in excess of that amount.
>> Perfect.
Oh, yep, 60,287
there is one of the volumes on the property line.
So
let's see. One of the other things we're looking to do is to do geothermal.
We'd like to be
do some eco friendly
stuff. We had looked at potentially
doing solar on the house, but when we went through wetlands,
it was shown that they would like as little disturbance as possible to the lot. There is a lot of tree cover here.
So we decided not to pursue
that
at this time.
So our intention is On
>> that issue,
Megan, because I see
you have
this little red line with
the little arrow
heads on it or whatever.
It shows the
extent of
I forget what you
He said proposed line of disturbance?
>> Yes.
If
I were to look at that
and look at your drawing that talks about the first thing you're going to do is cut
down the trees
consistent with what the Wetlands Commission was asking for that you limit that. I can't get a sense from the drawing
on
how many trees are going to be taken down or how extensive that clearing is going to be. And what I've seen on some other ones are a little line showing where
the trees would be cleared around the house just so we have
>> a better feel for that. This red line is that and it was the same as it was on the wetlands print at the time that we got approval. We did do a walk through with wetlands as well where we actually paid the engineer to come out and mark
where that
area of disturbance would be. I know for wetlands they'd actually come and walked through and seen it live.
So that definitely is something in that
was considered as far as as that in Mark Dunn.
So
his proposed limit of disturbance is this red line here.
So I will say from being living here,
there are definitely some old
trees that like I was walking my dog yesterday, there's a lot of branches that fall, so I think
some of that was keeping maybe some of the
dead trees away from the house kind of thing. There's some very dead trees in the mix in the woods here. So is what you're saying is that the pink
>> line in there is going to be the you're going to clear everything to the road in there?
>> No,
I don't think that we would clear everything to the road in there. He just said that that's the limit of where we would be disturbing
anything.
So like over here, most of it to the right is for the septic
and stockpile area. I mean, if you look at the house, it's not too too far back from the road as well
here and actually there is that whole section to the right that's not even ours where we're not touching that red line is goes back at a pretty steep angle away from the road
towards the septic.
>> Okay
and one of the things we'll talk about
after you're
done presenting is whether or not we as a commission want to go do the
sidewalk
on the property as well.
Okay.
Okay,
>> I would say that that's probably the main thing that you know we wanted to share is that you know we we definitely
love to have this project work out work and I would love to live in the town and live here next to my aunt.
Are exceeding
every.
Code that we've been asked to and will continue to exceed everything as far as building codes with the floodplain
my intention is to go through fema and.
You know, make sure that that is we've exceeded all their regulations get the letter map revision after the fact.
We are
it's important to us to do that we're building up.
Even a foot more above base flood elevation because we have been told by our engineer that
FEMA will most likely be redoing their flood maps
at some point their firms.
These plans are
essentially the same. You're seeing the color coding and such now to help make them a little easier to read but they're essentially the same that we've had since
we first applied
in May of last year.
>> Okay
and
that drawing
I see where you're going to go to an elevation where the house is proposed
of 325.5
feet.
Yep.
And
then there's another
it looks like a proposed elevation of three fifty four that I see down on
the south side of that.
I don't know if does that extend around? I don't see where that elevation extends around
to the back of the house or whatever. Or does it just drop off
fairly abruptly on the backside of the house down
to whatever the elevation there is, 322,
I think. Yeah, 324
>> he's got on the front and then
three twenty three around the side down to three twenty two in the back. So yeah, it does go down. It looks like two feet.
>> Okay, so that'll be a sheer drop from the slab down about two feet at that point. Yep. Okay.
And the flood elevation is three twenty three?
>> Let's
see.
Yeah, I think it was 323,
maybe.
I apologize. The engineer has all that. I think I saw it on the other map. Yeah,
>> I thought I saw 323.5.
So they were two feet above
the listed
flood height. I assume you got that from FEMA. Is that where that number comes from?
Okay. It
>> looks like you're going to be clearing half the lot in the front there. It's all going to be cleared.
One boundary line to the other is going to be cleared off, looks like.
It
>> does look a little more extensive than I was expecting
based on the comment that
we didn't want to disturb any more than we had to. I know they got it cleared to get the
septic reserve
but I am surprised that
and we'll have to go back and look at the wetlands
>> approval. I can't remember exactly. It's been a while. The limit of clearing is from one property line to the other and right out to the road. Yep. The one to the left, just so you guys know too, there is not very much trees to the left of the proposed driveway right now. There's a little bit, it's lot of like Pachysandra and more sparse
on the trees.
So I mean over there,
you know, probably be clearing just as much as I need for the well
over there.
So, as Andrew put, this is the limit of disturbance,
not necessarily exactly what we would be.
>> I've always seen clearing
limits on
every print I saw always had clearing limits not limit of disturbance.
>> Yeah and I think that would be
that's
why I was asking the question earlier about the,
you know, checklist talks about the trees 10 inches diameter and more. Right. We had some
of the mature trees, it would be nice to have those
left in here so that it wasn't a clear cut area.
Right
>> now it's showing that you can clear cut that whole area.
>> Yes, and I know we've been surprised on a couple other lots in town where we didn't think that was going to happen and we got
a lot more of the tree taken down than
we can. But we'll
see
if we want to do a sidewalk here in a few minutes and that can be one of the things we can look at when we head out that way.
Anybody else have any other questions
for the applicant at this point?
And I did have one
other request
for the applicant.
Somebody did an excellent job of preparing
a write up on all the different
requirements. I think it was section 10.8 when you went to the zoning board of approvals.
As
I look in our regs
10.7
I think it is has as a list and you said they pretty much mirror the FEMA
requirements
that
you would be
all exceeding. But I know I
had a hard time
checking through all these different requirements
for the development standards here for this chapter
and telling whether or not they were
fixed.
And that was,
know, new construction shall be anchored to prevent flotation
and something like that.
It would be So
very helpful to us to have that write up when we come to a public hearing to have that be part of the record that addresses those different eight
things in there, just like the zoning board of appeals.
>> That was one thing that zoning board of appeals had asked too as well. It was important to them.
Don't know if it is as much for you guys, but I'll mention it that one
member had asked if the town felt that they would have any legal,
you know,
repercussions if the house ever flooded or whatever and the answer to that is no from the town attorney that there's no liability
for the town as far as that goes because we're showing that we're building up out of flood elevation so that the structure structure is is safe. Safe. Okay,
yep.
>> I also wanted to point out, I reshared the old map. This is the same one from
wetlands.
It does have the same exact
limit of disturbance on it or limited clearing
for
the trees as well.
>> I look at that map it
the clearing is just slightly behind the existing house that's not very very far back.
>> Yeah and when you're here you know like I said when we've just had a few wind storms there are some very big trees here that that would worry me being maybe a little close to the roof in a couple of cases.
That's actually the existing house. I'm in now there's one or two we need to look at
soon that are dead and big.
>> Okay.
Megan, can you just
scroll your drawing one way or another so that I can see the notes on it? When I tried looking on the website today
to read all the notes on the drawing
and I blew it up to where I could read the letters, they all
they were sort of unreadable.
And I'm just and so I'm going to ask and so
I can read that. And so I don't know why when I looked at the Down website drawing,
I wasn't able to get there. It looked different to me.
But anyhow, I would ask
that
you know
we get
copies of the drawing for each
of the commission
members.
I think it said we asked you to supply 10, that would be more than enough that
we can go through and at least read all the notes. Because as I say earlier today,
I tried to read the notes and
it didn't turn out readable for me for whatever reason.
>> So Jed, you'd like 10 prints, like actual printouts of it or emailed to everybody?
>> Paper prints. The hard copy, bigger print so that we can
you'll see it you'll
have the chance to mark it up and all that kind of stuff and.
Okay.
>> It says number eight right here, clearing limits shall be flagged by a surveyor prior to any site disturbance.
>> And those are, it's done too. That's all flagged here on-site and the house is staked out as well
which we did for wetlands back in.
>> And does it say who the wetlands, the soil scientist was on the delineated
the wetlands?
>> Jim Iany.
John Aany. John Aany, there we go. I knew I got the J wrong when I said it.
Where's that noted on here, Jim?
Let's see.
>> John Aiani right here on the bottom, certified soil scientist.
>> And is there a drawing where he's actually signed that or we've got some documentation for that?
I am not sure I would assume so.
>> Yeah I don't know why there's not a signature there I will check into that.
>> Okay.
Any other questions for the applicants at this point?
Do you have anything?
>> When
we bring it back
in the public hearing, that's when we can go over the checklist, Jay?
>> Was going to discuss with the commission after we're done with the Phelpses here on
how that checklist discussion
could be more beneficial.
You know, we had Jim go through and show
us what he thought was NA, what he didn't think was NA.
We can certainly ask any questions about the checklist at
the public hearing. I don't know that we want to go through the entire checklist, all 62
or whatever
blocks there are there, I'd certainly be
open to anybody that had questions on any particular
issue on the checklist.
We can go through there as far as any other regulation
that went up. I just wanted to make sure that
we thought we were
close to having all the materials we needed so that if we chose to schedule a public hearing
at the next meeting,
we would be able to and we wouldn't be scrambling at the last minute
like we sometimes are trying to get all the stuff we need to
successfully build the public record.
I was hoping to get that done in a little more orderly fashion this time.
So if Jim said something on the checklist was NA and you felt strongly, no, that's not right. We ought to hear about it tonight so we can ask the applicants to
bring that to us.
>> Well, lot of them I thought were accurate but
I thought that there was quite a few of them that since it wasn't a flood plain that
it was kind of almost more important than being in the wetlands.
Like any of the drainage stuff.
>> If there's a specific
things I thought
on the checklist that
when it was talking drainage, was really talking about subdivisions
and that kind of thing as opposed to just
a piece of property draining.
>> Yeah I
believe the checklist referred to
proposed drainage
meaning drainage improvements.
There really were none other than maybe some minimal grading at the driveway.
>> But certainly as we go, you know we've got
a month before the next meeting if there's
things you think should be there you can email
Jim or myself and
we'll see what we can do to
make sure that we're prepared to discuss
those issues one way or the other when we get there.
>> So all I'm saying is that can we go back through the checklist at some point?
Yes we can. All
Jim did was read it.
>> Okay, well that's why I had it called up, but we'll do that here
in just a minute after
we're
happy with what
we want to ask the applicants.
Okay.
>> I have one question Jed, if I'm allowed to ask it.
Yep, go ahead Kevin.
>> I saw that the lot width was drawn behind the house.
I saw that too.
>> Doesn't our definition say that it shouldn't be in front of the building line?
>> Are exactly right because I had the same question that you just asked, Kevin.
And I said well that's not right it's behind the house. And I went back and looked at the definition
and it says not in front of the house.
And so I had
a different thought in my head
I expected to see the lot width line right
as
it
came to the front of the house
going to the East West
property markers there.
And then I went back and
said, well, let me check
that one, the
definition that we have listed here is correct
and it jives with what we've got in our actual regulations.
And it is correct. It does jive with what's in our regulations. And it just says,
will not be in front of the house.
So
it really doesn't say
how far behind the house it is. But I concluded that the width
line that they had here
fit
the requirement.
And
again, that's my layperson
understanding
if there's somebody here that has a different take on it but I
had the same
question in my mind as you just raised Kevin.
>> I can say too that our engineer worked directly with your town attorney back and forth to get that definition
worked out because initially when we were talking about it I know Jim Halsey had some questions on that so he deferred us to Mark. Yep, I went back and reread
>> our definition and it looks good to me. Yeah, I met with
>> the applicant and their their folks
and Mark Brantz
and
that came up and Mark was
happy with
how it was proposed.
>> Okay.
Any other questions?
And again, none, we'll go through the public record at the public hearing.
Megan, if you can
we're done with your shared screen. We'll go back and I'll ask Mindy to put the checklist
back up.
>> How would you handle the front yard requirement of 50 feet when it's in a triangle like that?
>> So
the 50 foot setback, is that the question, Kevin? Right.
I think as long as the house isn't within 50 feet of the road, I considered it okay.
>> Okay. I was just curious since it came to a point like that.
>> And again, that's why we have five members of a commission. If a question comes up and
we
can vote on it and that sort of thing to make sure that
we're complying. Okay, I see we've got the checklist back up
And
let's look, any other questions on the first 12
items on the checklist there?
Okay Mindy, if you could scroll down to the next 10 or 12, whatever fits on the screen good. Oh, this is the bottom. Okay, that's good right there. We'll finish up that page.
Okay existing trees of tenant in diameter.
>> Yep and that's,
you know I am interested if there's some large trees out there that we might work to retain those.
And I am used to seeing on the drawings, you know, where
large trees are specifically drawn into the drawing.
But
we'll take a look when
we get out there for a visit,
if there's interest in doing that.
So I agree that's
>> a concern, Scott. Okay, number 18, stormwater management.
No stormwater management.
>> I believe four seventeen isn't triggered until there's an
acre of disturbance.
That's why I said it wasn't applicable.
>> I think we had thought from our site walk throughs too before that there weren't any trees that were 10 inches
or bigger here on this side of the property
where this would be.
>> So
on that
particular question
on the section 4.17,
it says the following activities are exempt from these standards and it's development of a single family home.
So my
sense was that for
residential
construction of one house
not required to have a storm management plan.
Okay, Mindy, if you could scroll down to the top
half of the next page.
Okay, you move down to the bottom half of that page, Mindy.
Okay, head up to the
top portion of the next page.
And
I did have a question. Were the utilities going to be overhead or underground for this particular house?
>> Right, that was one that I had.
Jim was reading it so fast. Couldn't. Yep. I understand.
>> I honestly I don't recall off the end.
This came up when I went over the
checklist with
Megan.
>> Yep. Do either of the applicants recall whether the
utilities
were underground?
>> I believe that they were supposed to be underground
for a new home, but then, you know, Jim and I had discussed whether or not in a floodplain if they should be different. But then we,
I think Jim, you mentioned a few recent ones you had done that they were underground so that is the right answer to it so it's whichever the code is but we believe that to be underground.
Well subdivision would be underground. I think we were going to defer to the engineer on that if I recall correctly from our conversation. That might be it or the utility company that comes because they were kind of the ones that actually put them in right to the house.
Yes.
>> Well, thought is utility company will do whatever you ask. You ask underground, it'll just, you know, I think that's more expensive than overhead.
>> Prefer
underground obviously for storms and such, but I would do whatever you know, you guys say. Can
>> we get an answer to that question for the next meeting? It's just you'll confirm that
the utilities are going to be underground?
Yep.
Parking was listed on there. Jim, you remember?
>> On the print, I can't remember.
It's just it's not. No, it's not identified. It's it's a it's a single family home and there's I mean there's a driveway with
parking shown which is not titled as if I recall correctly.
I mean understand you know this this checklist is for any any special permit so I mean it's
designed to cover any commercial application as well.
>> So
should
a
residential home
have a
bump out on the driveway to allow
parking
beside what goes into the garage? Yes,
yes every house is supposed to have a turnaround.
>> Okay and I don't recall that being shown on the drawing.
>> He does have it a bit wider there. Could make more of a bump out off the
>> side of the house, No problem. Normally, what you see on houses are it goes out two spots perpendicular
to the driveway.
Yeah.
>> Anything else on what we see
here?
Then go ahead and scroll down to the bottom there, Mindy, please.
Okay, that's it.
Okay,
yeah. Any other comments on the checklist, Scott? No.
>> It was just going so fast I couldn't. Okay. I'll
>> take another look, you know, how best to do that.
Because once I said we're spending too much time going through a 57
thing checklist
we just need to make sure we're all
looking at it ahead of time so that
when
we go through it quickly,
we're ready to do that.
This is the first time we've actually made it through a checklist. So I thought this was a tremendous victory.
Okay,
very good. You can go ahead and close that up,
Mindy, please.
And
if there are no other comments I think that
concludes our discussion on the new business application
for 57
Hendy Road.
Is there any interest
in the commission about conducting a sidewalk on the property?
Oh we should definitely right.
>> Okay, so is that a motion that we should have a sidewalk?
>> I'll make a motion that we have a sidewalk. Okay.
>> Can I have a second to that?
I'll second. Thank you, Susan.
I did watch the weather tonight.
You know, this Saturday is the first day of spring.
Looks like it's going to be dry,
reasonable temperatures.
Is
Saturday morning convenient?
Is there anybody that Saturday morning is not convenient for?
Doesn't have to be this Saturday. This Saturday is just the one that we've got a weather forecast for and it looked nice.
So I would
propose what we've normally done.
Saturday morning work for the applicants?
Megan can you help us out with that?
>> I can't hear what
Bill said. I'm not going to be here but as long as he is I'm going be away this weekend but as
>> long as he's here. If you're going to be here, Bill, shake your head up and down.
>> Can you hear me?
Can you hear me? This is Bill Phillips. Yes, I can. It's
coming through garbled, but I can hear you.
>> So garbled because that's how I'm getting it also.
But yes, this Saturday would be fine with me.
>> I would
propose to the Commission Saturday morning at nine unless
we want to make it ten because we just shifted to daylight saving time and the sun comes up a little later.
If either of those work for me,
I guess we could split the difference and even make it 09:30.
So
>> for purposes of the discussion,
have the motion propose
a sidewalk this Saturday
at 09:30.
So I'll move.
>> And Susan, you second Okay, that Bhattavad
so we've got that out there. Any further discussion on the sidewalk?
Hearing none,
I'll call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
Scott?
Leigh Ann?
Yeah, you're on mute, Lee Ann.
And I can't see you, so I can't ask you to shake your head.
I'm going go on for just Can a you hear me now? Yes, I can. Yep. Okay, sorry. Yes, aye. Okay, thank you. And Susan?
Aye. And I vote aye as well. So
the motion carries five-zero-zero
to have a sidewalk this Saturday
at 09:30 at
57 Hendy Road.
Next order of business is should we tonight schedule
a public hearing for the next
meeting?
And so I would look for a
motion
to
hold that if we thought that was the right thing to do.
>> I move to have a public hearing at next meeting.
>> Okay.
Thank you, Anne.
Looking for a second. Second.
Thank you, Susan.
And let me just make
sure there's no holidays making us go short where we don't get the notifications out right.
It looks to me like looking at my calendar, the next meeting would be on Monday, April 19.
I see that's Patriots Day up in Massachusetts,
but I don't think that would preclude us from doing anything here. So
that gives us plenty of time to get the notifications out
and that sort of thing.
Any discussion on holding a public hearing?
Hearing none, call for a vote on that. Anne?
Aye.
>> Scott? Aye.
Leanne?
Aye.
Susan?
Aye. I vote aye as well. The motion to hold the public hearing
in
the April meeting
passes five-zero-zero.
Any
other comments on the application for Hendy Road before we close on that and go on to our old business?
Okay, that's it.
>> Thank you for your time and consideration. We appreciate it.
>> Well, I know it's been a long time coming from you.
Really did get the trifecta. You get to go to Inland Wetlands, SUNY Board of Appeals, and your planning and zoning as well.
Let's So see if we can get it wrapped up
expeditiously
>> for you. We appreciate that very much. Thank you. Thank
>> you very much.
Yeah.
Okay,
going back to the
agenda.
Now we'll head into the old business.
The first
item is an update, use of town owned property.
Jim, did you have anything to share with us?
Any communications with the Sheehan's over on
Wheeling Road since the last meeting?
>> I did provide one of the Sheehan's with a letter indicating
what the commission's
decision was on that. And I believe there is an application
forthcoming. Have not seen one as yet an application for for a single family home.
And I did address.
Comments that were raised
along that time relative to to notations.
In the both in the I think in the deed and the.
On the plan and there there were
there were explanations.
That
cleared up any concerns that folks had.
>> Okay,
any questions
on the Wheeling Road and use of town owned property?
I'm going to move on to the sign regulations.
And Mindy, if you can allow
me to
share a couple of things here.
I think you should be able to.
>> Yep.
Okay. Last time I gave a little PowerPoint presentation
on
signs and
I thought what I was going to do is just address
the
constitutional
free speech
issue with respect to the small signs and I started
as I walked around I paid attention to signs and I said wow there's a lot of signs out here.
And so I did a little bit more in-depth
look at our sign regs and I wanted to just go through,
spend a few minutes going through the different types of signs and that with everybody, look at some changes
that I'm
thinking
we would make to the regs so that you're all kind of with me and
having a conversation with you, getting some feedback, pushback
allows me to make sure that I'm heading off in the right direction. So I do have lots of pictures but I wanted to start out with the different
kinds of signs and that sort of thing in our regs.
And then maybe we have a little quiz show
what kind of sign is it when we put up a picture of a sign.
But anyhow,
this is from our current regs and heading down through the regs,
what I did on the very first intent paragraph is just added the words while ensuring the constitutional
right of free speech is protected.
So what that's going to do is that's going to
ensure that we have
we can have rules on signs
but we don't have rules on
content of the sign.
And we're making an effort to
protect free speech there.
So I thought that was pretty easy and hopefully no comments on that one. But again, if anybody does while we're going through this,
speak up.
I'm not sure that this is the best way to
go through this but
I'm open for better practices and that sort of thing. Then we got into sign function
definitions.
And
so we had a business sign here and
I won't read through that. You can see it but
I thought that was a good definition and I wasn't going to change. As far as I know,
we have not had issues
with business signs.
We could use a few more businesses in Andover where we could put up some signs, but right this minute
there hasn't been a lot of
comment about business signs.
So I didn't spend a lot of time on that.
The billboard, the key thing here is it's a sign larger than 50 square feet is a billboard
and billboards are prohibited in Andover.
Construction sign, just as a sign at a construction site and we've all seen those. Again, I'd welcome
the opportunity to put up a few of those if
we were building something.
The next one I struggled
with a little bit figuring out what it was talking about. Directional. A sign which guides or directs the public and contains no advertising.
And so I thought what this must be talking about is
when you come down
Lake Road
and you get to School Road,
we've got a sign that says school
and fire station,
that sort of thing. If we had a hospital, you'd have the hospital sign or something like that.
But I think that those are pretty much,
you know, that the town puts up and shows where
things are.
Okay, going on to identification.
And this was
I made a change here.
The sign on the premises indicating only the name of a professional or office building,
an occupied residential development, industrial area or park,
commercial shopping center or name of a school park, church, hospital or other public or quasi public facility.
And I said,
gee whiz, we are asking people to put
road
their street number sign out in front of their house so the ambulance can find them in a hurry.
But I didn't see anywhere in our regulations where
it talked about that. So I added a line here
on a residential lot assigned displaying the street address of the property.
And I did not put any
size restrictions on that.
If we get concerned about that, and I do have a couple of photos later on of different
kinds of street
address signs.
But I thought it was important that we added those signs because if we say no signs are allowed in the town right of way,
then we wouldn't be allowed to put up all these street signs that we ask people to put up.
Next one is nameplate.
Sign on the premise indicating name activity of the occupant or occupants of a professional
or office building
or the name and nature of a home occupation.
So as I walk around and
see that we've got a couple of home occupation things, I highlighted
that. I didn't add these words here.
I highlighted this because nowhere in our regulations
does it have any regulations
with respect to nameplate signs.
And
so I thought that when we got through, we wanted to make sure that we could put up a nameplate sign
if we had one. I was looking for the home occupation. What are the rules on those as I walked around?
And there were no rules.
I think they comply with stuff probably.
We ought to put that in there somewhere.
Novelty,
okay any sign, banner, pennant,
etc, you know,
displayed for a short period of time and so that
to me looks like a temporary sign and we'll
talk about that a little bit more.
I put a little banner out front of my house saying welcome spring,
happy St. Patrick's Day, stuff like that. And I think that's a novelty sign.
Public interest signs of a temporary
nature,
political education,
civil, religious,
or similar activity or event.
And so
I
saw
some article that I was reading where it's talking about the
free speech. It referred to
some of these signs and I agree with it, they're ideology,
ideological
signs.
And so maybe we would add that here.
I didn't know if a tag sale was
a public interest event or not but I thought I would add that in here too just because
it's a temporary sign and that sort of thing.
The other
signs that
we'll see show up later on,
a guy has somebody come out to their house, do some work and he puts a sign out in the front yard
out there normally in the right of way, you know, talking about tree service,
home repair, all those kind of things.
I guess that that's a public interest sign too and we can make that go there. I didn't know that it was particularly
in there but I don't see that
anywhere else. Like
a guy's building a house?
>> Yes. And we'll
show
I think
somewhere it
talked about
in the construction one and it must be down here under construction signs. We'll get there in a minute.
Public warning, I
take this to be like
stop signs,
speed limit signs,
curve signs.
But then you get into
no trespassing signs
and stuff like that. So some of them are by the town, some of them are by the homeowner.
In our regulations, we talk about the town can put these up. We don't say anything about homeowners being able to put these up. And the town probably doesn't put up too many no trespassing signs,
but homeowners do. So we'll want to make sure that that gets, you know, we're allowed to do that if we want that.
Sign offering for sale, yeah, we got that. That's pretty straightforward.
The roadside
sign looks like that's
for the farm stands.
And then we come down here next is a bunch of types,
definitions for sign construction.
And I'm not going to go through this. I didn't
any, I
didn't see where we had to change any of that because again there's not a lot of them and
I think we're doing
pretty good on those.
It talks about sign lighting, just natural and artificial, you know,
and I thought those were all okay. And the reason I'm going through here is I know we're going through quick. I don't want to put everybody to sleep too bad tonight.
Trying to point to where before the next meeting you can take a look at these things.
I will send this to Jim so he can post it on the website
and you can see my thoughts and you can figure out what's missing, what we need to do differently and be ready to hold that discussion.
So General Regs. So it says here, in addition,
and where I highlighted, I just highlighted to make sure I talked to everybody tonight on that.
In addition to specific sign regs is set forth in the following subsections,
the following general requirements
apply to all signs.
And it tells how to measure the height and width
on a sign. Okay, so I got that, no problem there.
The next one is really where we need to come through what we as a commission want.
And this is where it says all signs or part thereof shall be clear of all rights of way and no closer than 15 feet to the lot line.
And I added the words except we're specifically authorized
in these regulations
because we have all kinds of signs, the majority of signs pop up into the town right away along the road.
And
as we talked at the last meeting,
we like some of those signs.
There's probably some signs that we're
not as fond of. But again, that's the content. We can't regulate that.
I took away from the discussion at the last meeting that the benefit of putting signs in the town right away outweighed any
detriment.
And so
my thinking is that the Commission thought that we ought to not make it impossible to put those little temporary signs
out in the town right away.
I do think no closer than 15 feet to a lot line if we're talking about on each side of a lot.
You know, if you're putting up a sign you ought to be proud of it. Ought to be in the center of your yard, not next to the neighbor's yard so you're annoying the neighbor. And
I think that's pretty easy to comply with. So I like the 15 foot.
I thought our
discussion said we like putting them in the right of way. At
least to a certain extent and we'll talk about that again.
We talked about signs, you know, not obstructing
or impairing vision with normal flow of traffic.
No signs that flash, flutter, blink,
distract,
that kind of thing.
No sign shall be permitted which is directly or indirectly illuminated manner which may create a traffic hazard. Again, I thought those words were good.
Mechanical signs and billboards are not permitted
and I guess
I had visions of
the Las Vegas Strip where you have all kinds of signs doing all kinds of things. We probably didn't want that here.
The
next paragraph starts out intentionally left blank
and it talks about a sign that's erected prior to the effective date of this section, five years and all this stuff from 1958.
So I think the goal was probably to take that paragraph out because
five years from 1958 is long gone at this point and no longer applicable.
Okay,
it talks about
no construction signs displayed for a period exceeding eighteen months, unless the Commission grants an extension.
Construction signs shall be removed immediately after building project or last house subdivision issued certificate
of occupancy.
Okay, got that.
Signs shall be designed in harmony with building and established surrounding development.
All store units in the same building and separate buildings on the same lot shall have uniform design and placement of signs. The second part, that all sounds good.
I'm not sure.
I'm
a little
Having
signs in harmony with
your stuff is probably like
zoning regs
maintaining the character of a town. Know, that's
kind of, I don't know that we can
say it's going to be in harmony with free speech.
I'd be happy to hear anybody's thoughts
on that as we go through here if we need to take that out. I know it's a good thought but
maybe that conflicts with free speech.
I saw a couple of signs before the last election walking
around that
they didn't think promoted harmony
but
there you go.
And it just says that any violations of this in the next section,
officer can go around and
issue fines and it says the temporary signs, he can pull those out. That's down a little low.
Okay, so now
that's general signs. Now we're into the signs permitted in all zones.
It says the town of Andover may erect
directional signs of a size construction and lighting deemed appropriate for the purpose.
And I said maybe
that's I
started to ask myself who deemed it appropriate for the purpose.
And that's, you know, when we're doing that's kind of like the zoning commission. We can't do waivers anymore. We've got to
have
requirements
and
we spell it out and we can have
different levels of requirements. But
I didn't know who was the appropriate official
for
doing that. I thought I went out and measured a stop sign and it's two and a half feet across.
And so I was going to say,
you know,
these directional signs should be less than six square feet.
And that would include
the stop sign and that was
about the biggest of the bunch.
Again, think about it. I'll
update these some more, put in what I think it ought to be and you guys can tell me where I'm off the mark.
Down of Andover, May Rec, public warning signs. Signs.
Now again, this goes back to a public warning sign was a no trespassing sign.
And so I would not expect the town of Andover to be putting up trespassing sign,
but we should allow
residents
to put up a no trespassing sign if they want to.
So I've got to change that in my estimation to include
the ability and I've got a couple pictures of
no trespassing signs.
>> If there's no trespassing signs on some down on property that aren't supposed to be
trespassed on.
>> And I couldn't tell, I didn't know what those were. And the trees that I saw, these no trespassing signs posted on, all appeared to me that they were not in the right of way, they were back on the private property itself. And so
I considered that issue because we didn't want homeowners speaking
for the town saying no trespassing on my town property out here. Thought that was inappropriate.
That's
where I
had the concern about the public warning signs is that it,
again,
I don't know who deems inappropriate for the purpose,
but
if the town put up something,
we ought to be able to and we thought it was clearly out of line. I thought we could probably have a discussion with that guy and maybe he'd reconsider and we wouldn't have to
have a rule for it.
>> But what if the town has problems with trespassers on a property
that nobody's
>> supposed to be on for some reason? Well, and certainly the town can put it.
Thinking
where that might be
would be over. The
transfer station has a Yeah, that's the only thing that I can think of might be and
maybe
if they want to put some signs over there, I guess they're certainly welcome to do so.
But I would go so far as to say I have never seen a no trespassing sign
that wasn't
nailed to a tree.
When
we come down here,
signs shall not be attached to trees or telephone poles.
Wow, we got a lot of them. And I understand that the telephone poles belong to the utility company.
But if you got your own tree and you're putting a sign, I don't know that we want to preclude that. I'm
anxious for feedback on that too. We get down into
temporary public interest in novelty signs
and I added it used to be just public interest signs and so I changed it to temporary public interest because I thought they were all temporary and novelty.
And
I put their subject to the following additional
conditions.
And here I crossed
out a bunch of times and I gave up.
How
long would we like these temporary signs to be up?
And I came back to the last election where
our
previous regulations
always said thirty days.
And clearly with the
new
rules for voting in that,
if you don't put
a sign up until thirty days before the election, most people are already voted at that point.
And so
I'm looking at maybe
thirty days per quarter and that way you could have the two quarters that go neck and neck and that gives you sixty days before the election
or whatever.
Or we could just eliminate it completely but I didn't think that eliminating it completely is good either
because I go around and I see tree work signs that have been up for close to a year
and you know they're looking kind of ratty and at some point we just ought to stop advertising for the guy that cut down your tree a year ago and giving him that advertisement.
So I think we need to put something in there.
I just don't know that I have the right answer in there yet when I put forty days.
And I felt that it was inappropriate for, you know, at our discretion we could extend the total allowable time period by ninety days.
I thought that was inconsistent
with the free speech thing. That's regulating content. I thought
we would be
not well served to have that allowance in there.
So that's what I was trying to do for the temporary signs. I think we need to
limit how many there can be,
how long they can be up
and
we need to have a discussion of whether there
is a difference between a temporary sign on the town right away or on private property.
Okay, coming down further, all these rules
for
all
zone signs not be attached to trees or telephone poles,
I think it should just be telephone
poles or we could put trees but it's going to be problematic enforcement.
No sign shall be erected as to negatively impact sightlines. We heard that in a previous, I think that's a little redundant.
No sign shall exceed 16 square feet.
And that's
common to a lot of I thought, okay, so that's half a sheet of plywood. That's a good size.
That's for a temporary sign.
Maybe the folks for the election want to go, last year we allowed
up to 32 square feet, which is a full sheet of plywood. I didn't see too many of those as I drove around town.
I don't know if they push back and want to go the full 32 feet or not. But if we get up to 50, that's the billboard.
I can see where a business might need more than 16 square feet but for a temporary sign,
I thought 16 square feet four by four, that ought to be plenty.
And then we got the zoning enforcement officer authorized to remove signs.
Now we go down to signs permitted in our
specific
Andover rural design in Andover Lake District
and it talks about the construction signs. And again, if we had a big construction project,
they get 32 feet.
Each subcontractor
may display one freestanding
sign not exceeding four square feet. That to me looks like the little stick them in the ground signs.
And
I did not think that's what we wanted to apply
but it could to the guy.
This is the best place in the works for the guy who's the tree trimmer comes by and puts up this sign in your front yard. He's kind of a subcontractor to you.
And you come down here, it says height 10 feet,
illumination natural,
a permit from the zoning agent is required.
Now I would love to see us make a requirement that somebody comes in and gets a permit every time they put one of these temporary signs up in their yard.
That would certainly cut down the amount of signs.
But I think that's probably
not to be expected. And right now, I think the temporary signs
we should not expect
a permit for. If it's a permanent sign, you get permit. Temporary sign, no.
Identification
or nameplate, that's where we added that sign that talks
about the
nameplate sign was the
home business sign.
And so I see
Sears landscaping as I walk around. I see
Yeoman's Tree Farm as I walk around. I think both of those places
comply with
all these rules.
So I said, okay, we'll just put nameplate on there and that covers
our home
business things.
And it's got
Just those two and then this talk about apartment buildings or multiple family complex.
I haven't seen too many multiple family complexes around, but
I think we probably got one and
I
don't
recall what the sign is over there.
But permits are required for identification or nameplate signs with the exception of the property number sign,
oh, I did put a size in there, less than one half square foot.
And so
that's where I thought that anybody who had the bigger home
occupation
sign, needed to get a permit, you want to put your house number out front, no permit.
Real estate, and I could talk about that. Oh, this is 12 foot here.
I was thinking we would change it to 10 feet just to be consistent with every place else.
And that
gets us to the end of really talking about it. So there's only a couple lines in here that talk about these temporary signs and I don't think we've got it nailed
what we want to do.
So
not to bore you with
any more words,
A little blurry. I apologize for that. I guess I blurted out to protect
the guy who I'm advertising has had his sign out there for,
you know, a good six months or so.
I would assume that's in the town right away.
And
that's when when we set out, I was thinking that was that was the sign we wanted to most come
up with what we want our standard rules to be.
And so
do we want to allow that?
How long do we want to allow that? Need feedback on that?
Here I'm not commenting on the content of the sign. It was just the sign that I saw multiple varieties of as I walked around.
So here,
this one is in the town right away out by the road. It's also within 15 feet of the property line. So currently it would say that one should not be allowed.
This one up here is
back
15 feet from the edge of the road, 15 feet from each of the neighbors.
Clearly, I think that one is Okay. Jed, are you sharing those or sharing
pictures?
Oh, you're not seeing those? No.
I
got it. I called it up.
Now, how do I back out without having this all
we will stop sharing that.
Thank you, Scott.
Okay,
there you go. Now can you see it? Yeah. Okay,
very good. So this is
the little temporary sign that we
want to have our discussion about. What do we want?
Here's
the one that's within 15 feet of the adjacent property line and
it was probably within three feet of the road, so I think it's in the town right away.
Not sure that's what we want, but it might be.
Up here, we've got it 15 feet away from the neighbor's property
and well in excess of 15 feet back from the edge of the road. Clearly that one is on private property
and I think that's
okay.
Here I think this guy got tired of having his sign swiped
and so he put it up next to his house and
that's clearly on his property and
my sense is that's okay, too. So again, it comes back to like the last sign,
do we want the signs to be in the town right away out by the road?
And then to beat dead
horse,
I was curious,
did we want to have a limit on how many signs somebody could put in their yard? And
the example
regulations
that I suggested
that I look at
limited it to no more than two signs.
I
can live with two signs, I can live with more, but it ought to not be
100 signs.
So do we want to make
a reasonable number?
Is two or three enough and when we go to public hearing I will go out of my way to invite,
you know, the heads of the Republican Party and the Democratic Party so we'll get feedback from them but I'd like to
understand what the Commission thinks is best before
we go to public hearing.
These
are the
little identification
signs
that I've
seen. And here's
the little
one you get from the fire station to put out front,
that one happens to be,
I'm sure that's in the town right away. It's out fairly close to the road.
Here's another one that's
not
quite as good a look and sign but I guess it does the point. I don't think he is pointing to the story right down here. I think he's pointing to the house up the hill.
Anyhow, that's probably okay.
And here's a little identification sign by Screw Brook. I don't know who put that up but that's probably
Town.
>> That's probably okay too. I thought that was kind of nice.
So anyhow, those were identification signs and
I didn't really want to
adjust
what we were doing with them. I think people are doing the right thing. I just thought we ought to put it in our regs that you could put it up and you don't need a permit to put it there. And it could go into town right away because that's I think where we want them.
Here we get into these warning signs.
And
this is down, I think that's
on private property, I think that's Alma property,
but this is going down to the dam
and probably not the best
looking thing. I think a lot of the signs they put up now and the different rights of way are much
nicer but it certainly shows
that on occasion we violate the no putting a sign on a tree rule.
Here's
a newer
private property no trespassing sign again
on a tree and I couldn't find a no trespassing sign on anything other than trees walking around.
And here's a little canine,
you know, electric,
the invisible fence thing. And I like knowing when the invisible fences are there. So I'm walking around and the dogs are out barking and that sort of thing, they're not going to come run after me. So I thought we wanted all these things and I was going to make the regulations reflect that.
These
let's see.
So here's my little St. Patrick's Day flag out front.
While
the stand stays out there year round,
the sign, if that's a sign and it looks like it meets the novelty things,
gets changed frequently so I don't have it up there for an extensive period of time.
But we could limit that if we limit temporary signs.
Here's a flag
that's been flying and this has got, you know, a piano keyboard and some music stuff out here. I don't know if they're advertising
a home business
that they get piano lessons or not
by having that out there. But
certainly that's
a flag that falls into the novelty sign category.
And
if we want to limit that in any way,
and I don't know that we want to, but
again it's going to have to be consistent
with all we do.
But that gets on the verge of I
guess it can be taken down but it's been up there for probably two years now.
It's there. And then here's another novelty sign
on a tree,
on private property.
Why the chicken crossed the road? Rooster.
And on the other side it says, Why the rooster crossed the road? Chicken.
And I
don't know that we want to
discourage that. I think it kind of gives the neighborhood a little character.
On private property too.
>> Well, but our regulations don't specify anything different
between private property and the town property. I did not read our regulations to say these are the regulations if you put it on town property in the right of way.
I
assume
that the same regulations apply to private property because
when we're putting up all these business signs in that, the gas station or
any business in that,
it's all on private property where they put their signs.
Think,
I guess they got multiple signs. They get the sign out along the road and then they get the sign in the back.
But do we think we should make a distinction between private private property
in what we allow in the town right away?
I don't know the answer to that.
Nope, these are the warning signs. It talked about the town putting up.
And so here's a nice one put up by the town, stop sign. Here's a nice one, slow children at play.
And it talked about the town can put these up.
I don't know that I got a problem. This is on a telephone pole.
So that's
not so good. Drive like your kids live here. I thought
those signs were good ideas.
And here's your homemade
slow down blind driveway
sign.
So again, right now the only thing our regulations talk about
are the
signs that the town puts up.
Here's the Sears
town,
the home
business sign.
I think it complies with all the rules that we've got listed in there.
Hopefully he's got a permit for it.
Here's the Omen's Tree Farm. I think it looked to me about 10 foot high. It looked to meet the size requirements.
And it's certainly back off, not on the road
there so I thought that meant that.
Andover Lake, I didn't know where this sign fit. I guess it's kind of a nameplate sign that's the 32 square foot one.
It looks old enough to be grandfathered with just about any regulation that we put in there but
I'll try to fit that in someplace.
Anyhow,
there's,
you know, put this up at the last meeting, went walking around, it had blown down the next day, it's no longer up. So that one's gone. That was really a temporary sign with all the wind that we had. But anyhow, those
are some signs that I saw as I walked around. Again, I'm surprised at how many things are out there that we can
call signs.
And
with that, anybody got any feedback for me tonight?
Anything I said, look off target?
But I think the real heart of the matter is,
with these temporary signs,
how many, how long and
on town property or not.
And if you want, I will take a stab at putting something down on paper and then we can throw darts at it next meeting and see whether or not we think that's appropriate.
My suspicion is most people don't know we have signed regulations and so anything we put in here isn't going to impact a lot. But I do know that the
political parties pay close attention to it and they were eager to get their signs up last election and
we'll be going forward. So any questions for me on signs?
Okay,
That's all I wanted to cover on the new business on the signs.
I will stop sharing.
There we go.
Going on to frontage requirements.
I have not done anything. We decided we were going to
make a frontage requirement.
When we go to a public hearing and do some zoning changes, I will put that in there. I think that's a very easy
change to make.
When
is our next
>> public hearing that we could do that? I look at that being when we do the sign regulations.
I'm going to do signs and any other changes to our regs together and hopefully if we need any changes to the link regs we would put that in if we discover that there's any holes in that.
>> Can you have or
are you going to write up the frontage regulations?
>> Yes, yep I'll take care of that. I think that's easy.
Moving
on to commission vacancies.
I did get a copy of
what looks to be the
ballot for the election
in planning and zoning.
Kevin, you did not get your name on the ballot this time around.
I see there's three names, two Democrats and a Republican. Lee Ann is a Republican running again,
Brian Biggs
and Steve Nelson,
both from the Democratic Party are running for our
vacancies. And we'll have two open vacancies
coming up.
And Susan's name is on the ballot for
the open alternate position. So
run those
names
by me again Jed.
Steve Nelson,
>> Brian Biggs,
Briggs?
Yeah
Briggs, b r I g g s.
Those are new names and then Leanne.
Her
term is
coming up and she's running again.
And is Steve Nelson a Republican or Democrat?
>> I think he registered
with the Democrats.
I think he's an independent.
>> But he registered. He's going to be running as a Democrat? Yes. He went to their caucus and
>> asked to be put on the ballot.
That's just from a conversation I had with him out walking around the lake.
But I think he, I recall he said he was an independent.
And
what about Brian Briggs? He's a Democrat. So
>> has the official cutoff passed, Jed? Yeah, it has. Okay, yep.
Because I actually forgot about it and I emailed the,
I forgot what their name was,
the Republican representative for the town today, but I guess it was too late past the cutoff. Yep.
>> I think it was the first week in March was where we
made all the
running official there.
But anyhow, you'll get another chance, Kevin. It'll
come up again at some point.
But I'm looking
to have a complete lineup, which is great.
That's good.
So that's all I have to do on
commission vacancies there.
Training, workshop,
follow-up.
Scott, what do you think about the
the training?
Yeah, the Connecticut Bar Association
Land Use Training?
>> It was very good,
very interesting,
a lot of information.
>> I
thought the same thing
and so actually
I forgot
to look to see. I know they said at the training you would be able to
get a link to go to it. I know
at least I
would recommend it to any of you.
It
was
irresponsible
of me to be chairman without having attended that
training ahead of time.
I didn't really have the chance to
but I sure feel much better after having gone through that and they give you a nice
thick handbook 600 and some pages that has got all kinds of stuff in it that
I really feel much,
much
better able to have a clue about what I'm supposed to be doing now that I've attended that all day training.
So
Jim, can I ask you to see if you can find the link and maybe post that
on our website?
Yes. Somebody wants a book
and I highly recommend it to anybody who's on the commission
>> you Yeah, get
I'm ordering a couple of books one for for Anne because
she hadn't can't we.
I'm ordering one for Anne and one for
Bill DeRosier from CBA. If there's anybody else would like a book.
There's money in the budget for it. Let me know.
But Jan.
And Cremay? Yeah.
Cremay.
That's good.
She had intended to sign up and somewhere.
Yep.
Miss.
That way if I get the coronavirus
and die,
>> my relief will be nicely trained.
I'm not counting on getting that coronavirus.
I got my shots. I'm ready to go.
Okay, anyhow,
that's all I had on that really good training. You want to book, want to attend, let Jim know and we'll see if we can fix you up.
And that completes the old business.
Moving on to
approval of the minutes from the regular meeting of February 22.
Looking for a motion to approve the minutes.
>> I move approval of the minutes of the February 22 meeting. Thank you, Susan.
>> I have a second.
Thank you, Anne. Any
discussion
on the minutes?
>> I have one very my age on page two, item 4C,
filling vacancies.
I believe it should read Democratic
Town Committee
Instead of democratic commission.
Okay,
>> you're correct. I think we probably said democratic commission but we probably should have said democratic town committee.
>> I have a couple of comments. One is page two, second paragraph.
Yep. Use the term quick claim when it should be quick claim.
What?
>> The minutes use the term quick claim opposed to quick claim.
I'm saying quit being Q U I T. Okay.
>> Yep.
That's always been
a mystery term to me.
Okay. And
>> three, paragraphs two and five,
there's an 824 referral and it should be 824.
Okay. And
if I know Mindy
reported what was what was stated,
but I don't know if there's a way to put in that, you know, for somebody who's reading the minutes, that it's a reference to the Connecticut general statutes.
Just so that it's clear for whoever reads it reads them.
>> So how about so after the eight twenty four for referral we put in brackets?
>> That's what I was thinking. Yeah, Connecticut General Statutes.
Connecticut General Statute. Yeah, just so they
read. Yeah, that's my.
>> Usually it's written before it, Jed. Okay, we can put it. We can put it before but I know we didn't say it.
I know the minutes reflect exactly what was said,
but
you're right. And so if we put that in brackets, that does help clarify
what we're going for there.
That'd be fine. Okay?
Any other comments on the minutes?
>> This is Leanne. Can you hear me? Yes.
Yes, I don't have the minutes in front of me, so I'm doing this from memory. Okay. I think just a minor point.
I think it was
possibly under the signed discussion where it talks about referring to certain sections. I think it's just repeated twice.
I think the same sections
of the regulations
repeated.
It's 20, maybe 20 Okay, I see what
>> you're saying there. We've got
yeah, so
Mindy, on
page four of six,
discussion,
right in the middle of the page, the following regulations were reviewed and discussed.
And we've got 23.2.1
and 15.5.3
listed twice.
>> So it's not wrong it's just a little repetition. I
appreciate it. Then right
at the end I think maybe Scott Mader seconded the motion to adjourn and his name his last name isn't capitalized.
>> Correct, yep.
See that one, Mindy?
Okay, very good. Any other comments?
I would just like to recognize,
and you've heard this before, Mindy, what a super job. I
can only imagine as I read through this,
it can't be easy
to summarize
what it is that we're talking about
and get it concisely
down so that it only takes six sheets of paper. And so I thought you did just an
incredibly nice job on capturing
what it is that we talked about. Well
done. Thank you.
So
with that,
we'll call for a vote.
Anne?
Aye.
>> Scott? Aye.
Leanne?
Aye. Susan?
Aye.
And I vote aye as well. The minutes are approved, five zero zero.
Next item on the agenda correspondence,
Jim. Done.
Okay. Administrative
report, Jim.
>> Enforcement actions, 137
Chatty Mill Road. There was a utility shed that had gone up without benefit of permit. It since taken down.
And 44
Wales Road,
there's an outstanding
complaint regarding
someone living in
an RV. And that was agreed upon with both the commission and
the owner that he would take care of that by April 1.
So
>> when we come to our next meeting, we should have clean bill health over there.
>> Actually, I have both of those. My plan. Yep. Other than that, there's a lot of springtime activity.
I do expect a
house permit coming in for Wheeling Road. A number of folks are looking at lots
for development,
both old existing
lots.
Scott's Tree Farm apparently recently
has transferred,
and I got a call from a gentleman who wants to do something there.
So Vince, I haven't talked to him as yet. I just got the email today. They indicated they would give him a call tomorrow.
Other than that,
just so so folks know, we are now dealing with we now have the the town of Bolton
building inspectors representing or or covering the town of Andover
for the time being, and I don't know how long that is going to last.
We had some turnover in the office as far as
the
land use administrator has
left.
So we're dealing with that.
Can anybody hear me? Yes, yes, Okay.
>> With our land use and sorry. Yeah, was gonna ask what's the name of the land you ministry with that or was that Susan
Susan Madry that was her title.
>> I
believe
I don't know whether it was land use administrator or building administrator.
>> Jim, this is Leanne. I have a quick question about what you just said about Scott's Tree Farm.
Did you say it's been transferred?
>> Well,
that's what according to a gentleman that sent me an email.
Does that mean the whole property has been transferred?
>> I'm actually,
I believe I don't know how much of property. I don't know whether it's the property on Route 6 or whether it's I believe it's the property on Route on
Bunker Hill.
So I don't know how much of Russell's
property he has purchased the new owner.
>> Okay that's what I was getting at because usually
when you said transferred I just wondered because it's not the same thing as a transfer but there's that a cut above place that operates out of there so that wouldn't be a property transfer unless it happened to be the same guy. Was just wondering if what you were getting at is that an application was coming for additional office space for another you know
activity or something in there but you're saying it's actually been a transfer of property?
To my understanding, yes. Okay, thanks.
You're welcome.
On
>> the
shed that's being taken down, did we offer that guy the opportunity to put in
an application?
Or is it just a place that you know
it was
no good?
I mean we I hope we didn't go out there and just say tear it down.
>> He
was just given the regulations and he said I'll take it back there's nowhere I can put it and he took it down. Okay.
It was a metal shed that he just took it apart and
I don't know all the details. I'll pop up someplace else.
We're getting there.
>> The
Inland Wetlands Watercourse
Commission Liaison Report.
I've got
nothing to report at that point. At this point, I do expect that
the property, and we had talked about it a long time ago,
up on
Pine Ridge Road,
an application for
a open space
rear lot subdivision.
That will be coming our way soon, but it has not yet made it through the wetlands over there.
>> Quickly interjecting,
I don't know if we had a motion to approve
in a second for the minutes.
>> I made a motion. Yeah, we did have a motion.
I thought it was Leanne and Susan.
Could be her, Anne and Susan, one of the two.
I made the motion and Anne seconded.
>> Okay, cool. Sorry, I didn't I'll get
watch the recording to
get it down. Thank you.
>> Next
item is miscellaneous.
Anybody
got anything else that we should be talking about tonight?
>> I have a question,
I'm not sure I should go here or somewhere else, but I know Bill Phillips personally. So I'm assuming I would have to recuse myself
if I was seated.
>> Probably
that would be the best
thing to do. Yes. Knowing
somebody that covers a wide spectrum of
we all little towns, lots of people know lots of people.
Certainly we would not second guess your judgment to recuse yourself.
And that
always sounds like the best case whenever there's any doubt in your mind on that. Okay.
That's all I have. Okay.
Any other
for miscellaneous
here?
Jed, oh shoot.
>> Yep, I can hear you, Leigh Ann. Now your microphone just went off. Oh, I was just going to mention
that you and I listened to that forestry webinar.
Yep.
>> Which was pretty interesting. It was a little bit technical, which we had been warned about, but it was interesting.
>> Yes, and so
funny you should mention that because
before
that webinar,
I downloaded that application on my phone and I thought I was good to go. After that webinar, I tried to use it
and I couldn't
get it to do anything that we had talked about. So I didn't try but yeah that is interesting.
So
when
I mentioned that to Jim he said oh you want to talk to Scott.
And so Scott I know you've
application. I don't know if it's the same one that guy talked about but I
tried and failed as far as getting my phone to have all the applications that you used when we were
walking around out there on
Merritt Valley.
Right.
I might be looking for a
training session on that out of you at some point here. Well, what was it called? Force?
Well the
application
is
Avenza Maps.
Right.
>> Is that the one you use? The state uses that a lot. Yep that's what they were
talking about and I
just
couldn't get it to
map.
Is webinar
on the
internet now?
>> It should be.
And
you'd have to go, I'd have to go back and figure out
what group it was that we put that on. I think it was DEEP.
How much what was the application?
>> How much did it cost? It was free.
And you had a lot of neat stuff. I'm sure that they were recording it.
>> I'll see if I can drag it down. I think the free one is probably a trial for seven days or ten days maybe. No, it's
>> not as good as the professional.
But
the guy who was giving the presentation said that it is a great thing and
he was all in favor of you don't need anything any better than that.
Yeah. So I
guess I could always go back to him, but I
had enough other things going on that I hadn't felt like
>> dealing with it. And I was going to do that webinar also but I've
>> done too many webinars lately. Yep, there's been a lot of good training opportunities out there. Burnt out on webinars.
Can
probably forward it to you from last month.
>> I'd like to try the AdVensa thing because other people have told me they use it but the one that I use is real easy, it's accurate.
>> Yeah, a it's fair to be incredibly useful and accurate and
I'd like to have it just for going out hiking around
if nothing else. Won't get lost.
Okay,
and I know it's not on our agenda but
I will ask
Judy if you had any other comments for us. Stayed with us to the end here.
>> I did
And I really enjoyed listening to the conversation and
the items that you all care about.
I learned a lot from
plan review.
And I know that everybody's
now over two hours here and that's really quite a commitment that the board makes and that's very impressive. So not that my opinion necessarily means anything to you, anyway,
I find that to be impressive. So
yeah, thanks for what you do. You
really care about
>> the town and it shows. So thanks for letting me listen in. And you now know who agent Allisi is so when it comes time for you to build on that piece of property,
>> it would be awesome. I actually emailed him today. Oh, okay. Very good. I had no idea he'd be on the meeting but yeah I have a bunch of questions a lot of things to learn but yeah
I'll
get there. Well welcome to Andover. Thank you Jed.
>> And with that
does anybody
want to make a motion that we adjourn?
I'll make the motion. I'll show you more sign stuff.
Anne made a motion to adjourn.
Any second?
I second. Okay. Thank you, Susan.
Any discussion?
Hearing none,
all in favor say aye. Aye.
Opposed?
Thank you very much everybody
and we'll see you this Saturday
09:30,
Hendy Road.
Good night everybody.